hi everybody welcome back to Polar Ice
Creamery I'm Nick and today is a first
video of its kind for us where I'm
actually gonna look at a recipe one of
our subscribers sent over via Kofi we'll
go into that later
um they're trying to create a recipe
with oranges
oranges aren't really a problem that you
know to use an ice cream they're a fruit
like any other it's a citrus fruit
obviously they're not
particularly strong in flavor
surprisingly when you use them but what
I'm going to do here is do a two-part
video of the recipe that I've been sent
I've made it in its entirety and then
the next one or the part two for this
will be how we're actually going to make
the ice cream recipe for our subscriber
so make sure you like And subscribe so
you don't miss out on part two the
recipe that we've been sent
was
cream milk dextrose an orange reduction
skim milk powder
and then a medium egg
it's it's very short on ingredients
which is fine because you can make some
really good ice creams and gelatos with
minimal ingredients
but what they've done is they've
actually Juiced five oranges
and then added sugar to those and
created a reduction
and that is what we're going to do here
where we show you how we make this
person's recipe
so what we're going to do is we're going
to start with our five oranges these are
a medium to large orange we're going to
take those cut them in half completely
juice them put that juice back into the
pan we're going to turn heat on and to
that we're going to add 100 grams of
sugar it's just a straight sucrose and
we're going to boil this within an inch
of its life we're going to create
reduction by half so that means we
started here with about 210 grams by
weight we're going to reduce that down
to approximately 100 grams by weight
this is going to take a while this took
me almost an hour and that was really
boiling it heavy but as you can see we
got there in the end we took our
reduction out of the pan and put it in a
nice little pot and let that cool down a
little bit
then what we do is we start adding the
rest of our ingredients into the pan
because we're going to create this ice
cream base so we're going to start with
our milk and we're going to add the
dextrose and as you can see the orange
reduction has actually gone much darker
in color now I don't know why that's
happened I there's obviously a reason
for it but it's likely the exposure to
oxygen after the reduction process so
we're going to add that into our milk
make sure it's nicely combined and then
once it comes out to a slightly higher
temperature we're going to get our skim
milk powder in there and dissolve that
make sure it's completely homogenized at
this stage you add in your whole egg or
what I've actually done is used silk gel
because I was going to use an egg but
they had all gone off
so it's silk gel all the way what is
silk gel well I'll talk about that again
in a minute but essentially it is an
emulsifier and that is what you're doing
here you're emulsifying these base
ingredients
when that's ready and your egg is
completely mixed in we're gonna empty
that into a container and add in our
cream make sure it's completely mixed up
and put that in the fridge to chill down
after about three or four hours once
that base is chilled down in the fridge
you're going to take it out and pop it
in your ice cream machine as normal as
you can see here it really struggled to
actually freeze it and we'll talk about
why in a minute but after 25 minutes my
machine would not freeze this ice cream
to what I consider an acceptable level
so I decided to stop there take it out
the machine put it in a container and
stick it in the freezer
so we've got the orange creation here
we're going to get some scooped up and
see what the result is
[Music]
there we go scoop it was really soft
really soft and you can tell when I
opened the tub that it didn't have any
structure when I took it out the machine
it was super smooth on top
it's uh let's just eat some let's just
try it see what it tastes like
[Music]
okay
it's really odd it's really odd in
respect that
the texture is kind of borderline sure
but in a way but sherbet has much less
fat in it than this does it doesn't
taste of Orange
at all
really weirdly enough
considering what's gone in it it's
just very strange
so
silk gel
silk gel is mono and diglycerides of
fatty acids for you know the sciency
ones out there what does it do it
emulsifies your fats and Waters together
to create a slightly smoother texture in
your ice cream and essentially that is
what an egg yolk does
egg yolks have a certain amount of fats
in there not really enough to change
your recipe too much but they have
lecithin in there and less than is an
emulsifier and that's why custards have
a more luxurious kind of texture to them
because the Lesser thin allows the bond
of fats and Waters to become much more
stable within your ice cream environment
so you don't get lumps of this and lumps
of that it's all really nicely combined
and Blended within your ice cream base
now
eggs are much easier to get hold of than
silk gel or diglycerides of fatty acids
but
if you want to try silk gel Specialist
or special ingredients you can get
everything from them I do it's not an
advert from them I'm not affiliated with
them at all they just happen to sell a
lot of stuff that is really quite handy
for home ice cream makers so check out
our website I'll put a link below if you
want to have a look at what they do you
can buy it on Amazon pretty much all
over the world so that's a good place to
start
would an egg have changed this recipe I
doubt it there's some issues with the
flavor alone the fact it doesn't taste
of orange and it's not particularly well
balanced recipes it's obviously failed
for a few reasons I think but what we're
going to do is we're going to stop here
and I'm gonna
part two show you how we fixed this
recipe for our subscriber to create a
really strong nicely emulsified orange
ice cream
[Music]
awkward transition over I was going to
do this as a two-parter but my wife
convinced me to just link the two
together orange ice cream just to recap
from the first half of this video I was
sent a recipe by someone on Kofi which
is our version of patreon I'll put some
links below if you fancy supporting us
and that could be any way you like but
check out the link below any kind of
support that you offer will help
I made that orange ice cream to see what
it was like before doing anything the
only thing I didn't do was the egg
because the eggs I had in the house had
gone off
but
there were some intrinsic problems with
that and one
was it was a really gummy texture
it was kind of slimy in a way
it had an unusual texture because it was
an uh unbalanced or imbalanced recipe
for a few reasons actually but the
biggest problem that the ice cream had
was it didn't taste of anything
at all it literally tasted nothing it
didn't taste of orange whatsoever
and you think that with all that orange
juice it should that's actually where
Citrus ice creams differ because the
flavor isn't in the juice
the majority of the flavor comes from
the oils the essential oils in the rind
So when you buy an orange or lemon
extract
what you're doing is you're buying
something where somebody has soaked
orange rind
or zest into the base
glycerin or vodka alcohol something like
that
and created a much stronger
extract of that flavor so by not using
the stronger parts or the stronger
flavor part of the orange they really
missed a trick but then that's why they
came here to ask for help with this so
what I did was recreated the recipe
by using an ice cream calculator to get
the base ingredients in tune make sure
that the actual resulting ice cream is
going to be texturally right
and then we flavored it in a very
different way
how do we do it let's have a look
so like we did on the last recipe we're
gonna take our oranges these are much
bigger oranges than I used before and
we're gonna take three of these and
Juice them properly now look when you
see the orange cut in half there that's
all the juice that I managed to get out
of that first half and you know why
because I didn't roll it I didn't
squeeze it
if your oranges are not quite ripe make
sure you roll them on a Surface really
really well that loosens up all the
Flesh and allows that to release the
juice properly when you squeeze them
that one little squeeze I give is 25
grams worth of juice now actually in the
remaining two and a half oranges I got
the complete amount that I needed which
was 200 grams so that tells you how much
extra you get from the other halves
anyway enough about juicing oranges
what we did then we took our orange
juice and strained it through a sieve
into the pan we don't want those random
bits that was in the first version of
this ice cream it just wasn't good
texturally
once that's all completely screws in
that juices your pan you're going to
turn the heat on and then add in your
sugar we've added 160 grams of our total
sugar here there's 20 grams left on the
side and that's our milk powder at the
top but you're going to heat up your
orange and sugar base now you're gonna
get that water evaporating off what
you're actually doing at this stage is
you are creating an invert sugar you're
creating an invert sugar with the orange
juice and the sugars you already want to
use in your recipe it does take a while
to do but you need to keep an eye on it
when it's on the hob I took my eyes off
this mix for maybe 10 or 15 seconds and
as you can see it all boiled over I made
an absolute triumphant mess luckily I
was left with the 100 grams of mix that
I needed so what we did is take that I
put that back in the clean pan I added
in the last remaining 20 grams of sugar
once that was up to a suitable
temperature I added in the milk powder
again every milk powder is different
mine takes ages to dissolve but when
it's finally dissolved I
took the Rind from one of the large
oranges and if you listen closely
you can actually hear the essential oils
coming out and hitting those bubbles on
top of that base that's where the flavor
is
you're just going to leave that heat
taken over for a couple of minutes and
you're going to start to infuse that
orange flavor from the Rind into your
base
on stage you can turn the heat off put
the mix into a container and pop it in a
fridge overnight
[Music]
here we go
the ice cream has been in the freezer
for
almost a week
and just to touch up on a couple of
those elements the flavor comes from the
Rind predominantly not so much the juice
there is orange flavor or lemon flavor
or whatever such you're using in the
juice itself but the majority of it
comes from the essential oils in the
Rind that's why you steep that in your
base for a long old time and I took it
out the Rind just for churning as you
could see in the video you don't want it
in there really a to actually be
horrible but
you can and I love putting grated zest
or rind whatever you want to call it
into ice creams like lemon I do it all
the time
orange this is actually only the second
time I've made orange ice cream but if I
made it again I probably would grate
some of that in there it really would
boost the flavor but this flavor on here
is pretty strong as it is
but
remember the sugar stain the invert
sugar when you're creating an invert
sugar
remember that you're creating two
different strains of sugar than the
glucose and the fructose they have very
different effects on your ice cream
there's a whole list of sugars I'll do a
whole separate video on on the different
sugars and what they do to your ice
cream another time but
glucose and fructose will soften your
ice cream much more than
sucroseville
so what we're going to do get some
scooped up and then I'll show you the
result and we'll just go from there
[Music]
nice scoop it's a much more traditional
texture the ice cream had actually been
out for probably 10 minutes at this
stage but it does get reasonably well
from the freezer I'd probably say a
couple of minutes out makes it a bit
easier to scoop you can increase the
sugars if you really want to but I don't
think you need to
um color wise it's a much more natural
color the first one the orange
juice after that was boiled it went a
much darker color over it what's it
called I don't know why that is this
stuff didn't really do that so it's got
a much more natural kind of very slight
orange tinge to it so you know there's
no artificial colors in this it is what
you get from that oh
what does it taste like
really strong orange flavor
is what you want nice texture
no ice crystals in there
it's just a smooth
natural no add-ins obviously in this
this is just orange I mean this could
work you know a reverse chocolate orange
ice cream with chocolate chocolate
in there that would be quite a nice I
imagine
but it's a really nice straightforward
orange ice cream cuts through that
Citrus will cut through heavy things you
know so you can use this with maybe a
brownie or some chocolate cake or
something it'll cut through that dense
chocolate fatty kind of
cake or whatever it is that you're
eating with but
this is a really really nice ice cream
if you want something simple like a
lemon orange you know any kind of citrus
fruit you'll make it the same way just
substitute the fruit itself and what
you'll be left with is a really nice
pungent flavor ice cream natural colors
hope you try this one don't forget to
like And subscribe and we'll see you
next time
also don't forget
you can send us messages on Kofi I'll
put the link below on the screen and in
the description if you want help with
your ice cream recipes you can hit us up
there and we'll sort out any recipe you
like or any other questions relating to
your ice cream you may have so hopefully
we'll see you there
[Music]